"Plant-Based vs. Meat-Based Meals
for Weight Loss by Boosting GLP-1"
Vegetarian diets appear to offer
significant benefits
for weight reduction.
Might the appetite-suppressing
hormone GLP-1
have anything to do with that?
Let’s compare
the GLP-1 inducing effects
of a meaty meal
versus a plant-based one,
with the same
number of calories
on gastrointestinal
hormone responses.
I mean, we know that
the intake of meat,
particularly processed meat,
is a dietary risk factor
for diabetes.
Meat intake impairs
insulin sensitivity
and leads to increased
oxidative stress.
However, its effect
on the secretion
of after-meal gut hormones,
like GLP-1, has been unclear.
So, what happens when people
either with or without diabetes
eat a pork burger with cheese
versus a plant-based burger
made with couscous and oats?
For those with diabetes,
there was a doubling of GLP-1
half an hour after
the plant-based burger
was eaten compared
to the meat burger.
But if you compare
the two meals,
although they were
matched for calories,
they were not matched
for macronutrients.
The meaty meal
had more protein and fat,
fewer carbohydrates,
and since different macros
can affect GLP-1 differently,
the difference
in GLP-1 secretion may have
had more to do with the macros
than the meat.
Okay, so how about using
a tofu burger
that’s macronutrient matched?
People with diabetes had
a significantly higher increase
in GLP-1 release
after the veggie meal,
compared to the meat meal,
just like in the last study.
But if you remember,
in the last study,
the veggie meal only seemed
to boost GLP-1 secretion
in those with diabetes.
Was that because of
the macro mismatch as well?
There’s only one way
to find out.
A randomized crossover trial
tested the effects
of two meals matched in calories
and macronutrients
using the same tofu burger
versus
a conventional meat burger,
and compared to the meat meal,
the vegan meal boosted GLP-1
levels by 42 percent
in those with diabetes
and was about just as effective
in boosting GLP-1
in those without diabetes.
Does that actually translate
into improving satiety, though?
Yes:
"A plant-based meal increases
gastrointestinal hormones
and satiety
more than an energy-
and-macronutrient-matched
processed-meat meal
in type 2 diabetic,
obese, and healthy men."
Satiety was greater
in all participants
after the vegan meal
compared to the meaty one.
And since enhancing satiety
is one of the major challenges
in the dietary treatment
of obesity and type 2 diabetes,
plant-based meals
may be an effective strategy
in solving this problem.
But does this actually translate
into eating less?
Researchers had
study participants consume
a pasta lunch
at an all-you-can-eat buffet
with either
ground plant-based meat
versus ground beef,
and participants consumed
significantly fewer calories
of the pasta with
the plant-based burger meat.
Yet, despite eating less,
they felt just as satisfied,
full, and satiated.
But this was unlikely
to be a GLP-1 effect,
since rather than GLP-1
driving lower food intake,
lower food intake appeared
to drive lower GLP-1.
If you look at the effects
of mycoprotein,
which make up
meat substitutes like Quorn,
made from the mushroom kingdom
rather than the plant kingdom,
mycoprotein not only shows
a decrease in calorie intake
at an all-you-can-eat meal,
but so suppresses
subsequent appetite
that there’s a decrease
in intake over the entire day.
When researchers compared it
to eating chicken,
they saw a significant
decreased calorie intake
during the mycoprotein meal
that was not compensated for
later in the day,
which led to an average
caloric reduction
over the whole day
by 188 calories.
And, this was accomplished
without altering GLP-1.
So, GLP-1 may not be the reason
plant-based meals
tend to be more satiating
or why whole food
plant-based diets
apparently achieve greater
weight loss than any other diet.
Maybe it’s because
plant-based diets
are associated with
an improved gut microbiome,
increased insulin sensitivity,
better metabolism,
reduced caloric density.
Dietary fiber alone
can improve your microbiome
and reduce calorie density,
and a few types of fiber
may be able
to also boost GLP-1.
I’ll cover that, next.